it's available sister
in the middle length discourses number
three the Buddha commends one of two monks
the Buddha commends one of two monks
who upon arriving late for a meal
abstained from eating his leftovers
instead he chose to go without food
following the Buddha's Council to
prioritize inheriting the dhamma over
material possessions
and the Buddha stated that this
contented approach would ultimately
benefit that monk in the long run but
why and how does having fewer wishes Aid
in understanding the Dumber
it's basically
aligning your way of living
with the correct
correct
understanding of the nature of things
which is the Dharma
understanding the dhamma you can't
really do it from a just a purely
theoretical point of view one of the
first things you have to understand if
you want to start
practicing you know but you can you can kind of get
you know but you can you can kind of get
the idea of it but there's many people
who can do like a PhD in the Dharma
and but they won't really have any
understanding of it so actually
developing understanding is on the level
of starting to actually
align your life
with those principles that are
um that are spoken of so like having
fewer wishes for example
um or being content with little not
being greasy being
um
relatively minimalistic or having a
simple life
it's aligned with the
with the practice of Dharma because it's
already going to be developing your mind
in having less proliferation of greeds
not being not just reacting to uh to
things that aren't exactly as you want
them to be so like in this case for
example that monk he could quite well
have felt justified in saying oh well
I'd missed my lunch and I was you know
and I'm hungry and now somebody is
offering me food
um and
but he actually
chose to prioritize
um contentment even whether he got what
he wanted or he didn't get what he
wanted you can see he was doing that
obviously for the purpose of developing
a strength of Mind in the face of his
own desire because well the basic of
understanding the dhamma the Four Noble
Truth says that
the cause of any suffering whatsoever at
any time is your desire and so if you
want to actually understand that you
have to start practicing towards none
desire which you know you won't initially be
which you know you won't initially be
able to kind of do perfectly
but you can start by kind of limiting
yourself and saying no to yourself in
terms of things that you would
like to go for
and that you can say well is it is it
really necessary do I really need it do
I really have to have it is it
absolutely essential and so
obviously that then doesn't mean that
you know in this case it's this this
monk that day he went hungry
and obviously in that case it was for
right reasons it was for it to train
himself in
um in becoming content even when you
know when his body was hungry and
putting up with us but then that doesn't
mean that like in every case you should
always just go hungry all the time and
starve yourself that's something to bear
in mind because that's very easy then to
kind of fall into the Other Extreme of
just you know say okay non-desire and
you know say okay non-desire and
training and non-desire means that like
okay I must uh I must never put on a
coat when I'm cold I must never go to
sleep when I'm sleepy and that's not the
case so like it kind of depends why
you're why you're doing is and what you
can sort of discern are the are the
correct reasons and in this case that
monk obviously
you know you can kind of lean a bit
towards the side of more accessible
asceticism because that will be you know
still a bit safer than leaning towards
the side of just letting yourself do
whatever you want but at the same time
you have to be Discerning that middle
ground which is the middle way and that
comes down again to basically under
starting to understand the Four Noble
Truth so aligning yourselves with those
four noble truths the middle way being
the the path or the way to actually
um free yourself from suffering through
um up bruising the the desire that is
maintaining that suffering you need to
be kind of under to training yourself in
seeing where that desire is
because you can't you're not necessarily
seeing it right from the beginning
there's not really something you can
just kind of get the idea of on a
theoretical level
because actually if you are
understanding it fully if you're like to
understand it properly is to be free
from it that's what getting the right
view means
so it's um it's something you have to
like gradually train yourself towards
and start
um aligning your lifestyle with